<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Combate betweene tvvo seconds. One for obeying the present government, the other, the second part of a demurrer, undeservedly called religious.</title>
            <author>Ascham, Antony, d. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3918C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E562_16</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50805910</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50805910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75689)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E562[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Combate betweene tvvo seconds. One for obeying the present government, the other, the second part of a demurrer, undeservedly called religious.</title>
                  <author>Ascham, Antony, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 [i.e. 19] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Antony Ascham.</note>
                  <note>A defense of Francis Rous's The lawfulness of obeying the present government (1649) and an attack upon A second part of the Religious demurrer, by another hand (1649).</note>
                  <note>Error in pagination: p 1 numbered p 2.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint within single line border.</note>
                  <note>Headpiece and initial.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rous, Francis, 1579-1659. --  Lawfulnes of obeying the present government.</term>
               <term>Lover of Truth and Peace. --  Second part of the Religious demurrer.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Authority --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COMBATE betweene TVVO SECONDS.</p>
            <p>One for obeying the Preſent Government.</p>
            <p>The other, the ſecond part of a DEMURRER; Undeſervedly called RELIGIOUS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JAMES. 1. 26.</bibl> 
               <hi>If any man among you, ſeeme to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart; this mans Religion is in vaine.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright,</hi> at the Kings Head in the Old-Bayley, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165237:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165237:2"/>
            <head>A Combate between two SECONDS, One for obeying the PRESENT GOVERNMENT; The other, the ſecond part of a DEMURRER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a Scholler of the lower forme doth offend, the Uſher takes him into his hands for correction; And this Demurrer being of the lower forme, at leaſt in regard of charity, I think I may make bold to beſtow ſome chaſtiſements, if not upon him, yet upon his faulty workes. <hi>The wiſedome that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and without partiality.</hi> Therefore to be impure, unpeaceable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and partiall; muſt be the wiſedom from below, and brings him down to a very low forme, that is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165237:3"/>
            <p> This Demurrer wanting ſtrength in his Arguments, or doubting of them, thinkes to fortifie his diſcourſe, by laying ſcandalous and uncharitable ſuſpitions, on the perſon of him that wrote for obedience; neither are they uncharitable only, but untrue; and ſuch that upon the proofe of them: the Demurrer would hardly adventure a ſmall ſumme of Money, though he thus eaſily adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his ſoule: And yet <hi>he ſayes he ſees,</hi> (and becauſe he ſaith ſo, his ſinne remaines, for an untruth is never tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeene) and without reſtitution, and reparation, hee cannot expect his ſinne ſhould be taken from him. He ſaith, <hi>He ſees that it is a great ſnare to be poſſeſt of great eſtates by that power which can diveſt them, if they aſſiſt not their wicked deſignes;</hi> And that the <hi>Author</hi> he ſpeaks of, <hi>is entangled in this ſnare, or elſe he would never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Patronage of ſo bad a Cauſe.</hi> For anſwer; Firſt, This man cannot poſſibly fetch any convincing proof, or demonſtration of that which he ſaith, <hi>He ſees;</hi> But fetches it wholly from uncharitableneſſe; even a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety to that charity which thinketh none evill. This <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> is all, becauſe the Author will not comply with this mans errors and party. And whereas he calls it <hi>a bad Cauſe,</hi> certainely it may be good ſtill; for he hath very badly proved it to be bad. And why doth he not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and <hi>Gualter,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr,</hi> for maintaining a bad Cauſe, and doing it for a place of Profit. As for any deſigne, the whole life of the Author ſhewes him very cleare of deſignes; And for this, be it what deſigne it will be, he was no actor in it, but a ſpectator onely, untill he ſaw a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſet on foot, and that juſtice might be had this way, and no other. And then having a right to act, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165237:3"/> beleeved that he might exerciſe it in juſt things; yea he beleeved that it was a duty, though the Government had been taken by deſigne, and force, that thoſe who had taken it and excluded all other, ſhould give Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and if he aſiſt in that which is good, and which ſhould be ſinne if it were not done; I thinke it goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſkill of this Demurrer, juſtly to charge that which is good, with Sinne and Guilt. Sure it is that he had the councell and conſent of impartiall Authors, (and ſuch are the dead, not intereſted in our affaires) even Authors to whom this Demurrer is but an Infant, eſpecially if this diſcourſe be the top of his ſtrength, as it ſhould be, or elſe he is falſe to his Cauſe. For a more weake, irreſolute and unreſolving paper, is ſeldome ſeene; for in it there are ſo many [perhaps] concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the chiefe points in queſtion, that he ſeemes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved himſelfe; and how can he then reſolve others? But of this more in the concluſion; And now becauſe his matter is weake, therefore his chiefe ſtrength is laid upon ſcandalizing the Author; and ſo his beſt argument is his owne uncharitableneſſe; I am therefore the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in this point to make a plaiſter proportionable to the large poyſon of this ſerpentine Diſcourſe, that bites the Heele, when it can not come to the Head. In the meane time he may learne to conſtrue his Latin, by his owne actions in Engliſh, <hi>Scelere tuendum eſt ſcelus. That a falſe Doctrine muſt be maintained by falſe Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to make manifeſt that the Author is not ſo fixed to the world, as to maintaine a bad Cauſe, for a place of profit, let the Demurrer firſt know that this Author at the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing of the ſelfe denying Ordinance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165237:4"/> gave his vote clearely for the quitting of his place, and did verely thinke it gone, (whereof he gave very good teſtimony) but that it pleaſed the Houſes, to declare it to be without the intention of the Ordinance. So it ſeemes he hath beene able to quit ſuch a place for the good of the Publique. Secondly for the employments of the profits of his place. He hath ſo communicated them, amidſt all theſe ſales of Lands, and other oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities which are now going, that he hath not encreaſed his eſtate by purchaſe one five pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> But thirdly, with giving maintainance to poore Schollars' in Vniverſities, fatherleſſe and poore Children in Schooles, diſtreſſed perſons of <hi>Ireland,</hi> poore in <hi>Weſtminſter, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the Country, poore ſervants of the late King, poore diſtreſſed Widowes of Souldiers, and ſuch to whom Arreares are due, and maintainance of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he hath gone beyond any for ought I know, that have five times his Eſtate. And for getting of reward or advancement by this worke, it is certaine he tooke a courſe to the contrary; for he was ſo farre from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting any that are eminent in power, and can give advancement, either with the worke, or with the Name of the Author, that he communicated them onely to one that tranſcribed it, whom he adjured to ſilence. And of this concealing, the Stationer for whom it was printed, can give ſome teſtimony. True it is that upon conference, which he had of this ſubject with ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or by knowing his ſtile, ſome might adventure to put his name upon the worke, among which Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall</hi> is one, who being preſent when the worke was communicated to one of the Authors neareſt friends, in a cloſe and concealed manner, and thereupon reading
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165237:4"/> it, gave his judgement concerning the Name of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, though he had never any hint of it by any notice from the Author.</p>
            <p>But now to the Demurr it ſelfe:</p>
            <p>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>That he heares few rationall conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious men are ſatisfied with the Declaration of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> It may be he converſes with few men, ſo ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſcientious as to be free from partiality: But how unſatisfying ſoever it be beleeved, the Author tooke his ground upon a ſuppoſed unſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>a people may</hi> [perhaps] <hi>lawfully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey a Government, when there is no probability of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their loſt Government.</hi> If he would leave out this word [perhaps] wherewith he much troubles his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the buſineſſe is neare at an end. For the Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves there is no probability in ſight, and therefore it ſeemes he may have leave of the Demurrer, to approve of obedience to the preſent Government. And herein it is deſired that this irreſolute writer would reſolve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe better out of thoſe, that as it ſeemes have more knowledge and judgement to reſolve then himſelfe, and particularly that in this point of probability, and poſſeſſion, and others of kin to it, he would looke into Mr. <hi>Aschams</hi> diſcourſe, and either beleeve it or confute it; It is ſtrange that theſe men ſhould ſwallow that worke of many ſheets, and ſtraine at this ſingle one; But indeed till that Booke be anſwered, <hi>Calvin, Bucer, Peter Martyr, Gualter, Paraeus,</hi> confuted with the grounds and reaſons of thoſe judicious Caſuiſts (who though of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet in theſe caſes of juſtice, not in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165237:5"/> controverſie betweene us, cannot be rejected as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) the cauſe ſtands good, though the Demurrer in his bad language calls it bad, but leaves it good by his doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſayings, and his weake reaſons.</p>
            <p>Pag. 3. He acknowledgeth, <hi>When an unlawfull power commands; a man, [perhaps] may obey;</hi> So [perhaps] the Doctrine of obeying unlawfull power may be true, and the Demurrer goes about to confute a Doctrine which himſelfe confeſſeth may be true.</p>
            <p>And then with another [perhaps] he ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Judah <hi>knowing none of the Regall Seed ſurviving, [perhaps] Submitted to</hi> Athaliahs <hi>Government.</hi> A moſt frivolous, and ignorant [perhaps.] For beſides that God had promiſed, that <hi>Davids</hi> ſeed ſhould not faile; <note place="margin">2 Chron. 21. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the high Prieſt knew, there was one of that ſeede alive: And why did not he preach this Demurrers Doctrine to the people, that they ſhould not obey the preſent Tyrrant, and that by it they eſtabliſhed Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; betrayed the title of the juſt Heire? But no ſuch <note place="margin">2 Chron. 22.</note> Doctrine appeared, but the daughter of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> (very farre from any Title to the Crown of <hi>Judah)</hi> was obeyed ſix yeares. Beſides, ſee here the ſlightnes of this man, (whoſe Doctirne generally is a perhaps and adventure) doth not the very Text ſay, <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> the high prieſts wife, was Daughter of <hi>Jehoram</hi> and <note place="margin">2 Chron. 22. 11.</note> ſiſter of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> the late King; And if ſo, was not her Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better then that of <hi>Athaliah</hi> a ſtranger?</p>
            <p>Item, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. He ſayes, <hi>The Author concludes more then he undertook to prove.</hi> But would the Demurrer be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, if a man promiſing to give him ten pounds, doe make his guift twenty? And whereas he would gladly know, <hi>what difference betweene lawfull and unlawfull</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165237:5"/> 
               <hi>powers, if both neceſſarliy muſt be obeyed;</hi> Here indeed by confeſſing his ignorance, he might deſerve pardon, if it were not affected; For, he might know from the Caſuiſts, that the one is given as to a perſon comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by Right of Title. The other by an interpretative conſent, and <hi>pro tali rerum ſtatu,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he preſervation of the Common-Wealth; which is in ſuch a ſtate that it would otherwiſe be ruined. If I muſt give money to a poore honeſt man for charity, and to a thiefe for ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is there no odds betweene an honeſt man, and a thiefe?</p>
            <p>As for his rejecting the interpretation of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Firſt, he argues from a ſingle late writer, but ſhewes not from him what the Text ſpeakes againſt obeying a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that wants right, but of a Tyrant that does wrong. For he writes that this Tyrant, is a Terrour to good workes: Now we know a Tyrant in Title may be an encouragement to good workes, and ſuch there have beene.</p>
            <p>It is commonly ſaid that ſome of the beſt lawes were made under <hi>Richard</hi> the third. But Secondly againſt the Demurrer and his interpretation, are the judgement of theſe Pillers of the Church; who underſtand that this place affirmeth <hi>the preſent powers to be the Ordinance of God, and are to be obeyed.</hi> Thirdly, let one Greek word be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Power or Force,</hi> and the other <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Authority or Magiſtracy;</hi> Though <hi>Nimrod</hi> by the former did obtaine the latter; Yet <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſayes that his Authority gotten by power was of God. And ſo by vertue of that Text was to be obeyed; See that place, and others alleadged upon this very Text, by the Author in the laſt Edition, and they will abundantly overpoyſe this ſingle Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165237:6"/> opinion, both by reaſons and Authority.</p>
            <p>Pag. 4. He comes <hi>to</hi> Caudius <hi>and</hi> Nero, <hi>And firſt ſaith, That the Apoſtle might meane it of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny other p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer abſtract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly from the Romanes.</hi> So that he will have the Apoſtle moſt impertinently, to tell the Romanes what obedience is to be given by others in another ſtate, but not by them in their owne. Secondly, Let him remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that as <hi>Peter M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtyr</hi> ſaith, the Romanes had now gotten the Empire of the world; And then what was the ſtate, this Demurrer would have the Apoſtle to meane? Thirdly, He ſayes nothing to <hi>Claudius,</hi> who was ſet up directly againſt the Councells and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Senates: Neither was there following a free conſent. But yet further, If the Souldiers ſet up a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour or Government, and a conſent be ſo gotten, let this Demurrer talke with his learned Councell, and then ſpeak out plainely, whether Votes gotten by or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der force be valid. For in ſome caſes they ſpeake aloud they are not: Yet it ſeemes they are, when they may make for their turne. Fourthly, he ſpeakes of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Caeſars Title: But was not that Title inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by a triumvirate? And had not <hi>Claudius</hi> a Sonne when the Souldiers made <hi>Nero</hi> his Succeſſor? Doth not this man betray his maine buſineſſe by yealding; That he who is not the Heire, may be a lawfull Succeſſor, though an Heire be living?</p>
            <p>To the obedience given anciently in this Kingdome and yet continued to lawes of uſurpers, <hi>He anſwers ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally with doubts, and ſuppoſes according to his irreſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute manner, and ever and anon, comes in which the uſuall burden of the Song; Oathes and Covenants with a paire of [perhaps.]</hi> And whereas <hi>he would lay this obedience on</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165237:6"/> 
               <hi>the darkeneſſe of the times by Topery;</hi> Certainely there were very good Lawyers in times of Popery, and in thoſe point, Popery did not darken wherein it had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe. Our preſent Lawyers fetch the maine ground of their profeſſion, from Lawyers that were Papiſts, or in times of Popery. And it would be a weak and ridiculous anſwer at a Bar to ſay; That <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cton, Forteſcue,</hi> or <hi>Ploydon,</hi> were Papiſts, or under the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Popery, and therefore their Teſtimony muſt be rejected; and as little truth as law he ſhewes, in ſaying that theſe Lawes have beene ratified by ſucceeding Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, which he ſhould have produced: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut to Salve all, he concludes, that [perhaps] till then not to be judged valid in Law. But were they not held valid and obeyed by the Generation that made them? and that this man will not alow us to doe. But Secondly, let me anſwer him, that if he onely ſay <hi>[perhaps]</hi> they were not valid, he leaves roome for another to ſay <hi>[perhaps]</hi> they were valid, for one [perhaps] leaves roome for another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 5. To the Teſtimonies of Divines and Caſuiſts, And firſt to that of <hi>Azorius. He moſt diſcretly anſwers, That there was a tacite conſent of all;</hi> And is there not ſuch a one now, all men being taken for reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For it is ſuppoſed, every man as a rationall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould, and doth give his conſent; But it is ſeene by his reaſoning, that every man is not <hi>de facto</hi> a rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall man. To the reaſon of the Second, He with a [perhaps] ſaith, <hi>It is a Popiſh Nicety;</hi> But this a blunt anſwer to call all that Popery, which he c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n not anſwer. And if acute reaſons of Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, muſt be Popiſh Niceties, what will he leave for Proteſtants but Duncery? But in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165237:7"/> queſtions that concerne not Popery but Reaſon and Juſtice; why is the word Popiſh brought in, but to caſt a blemiſh on that truth, which he cannot otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute? In rationall things and not of Popiſh concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is farre more ſatisfactory to heare a Papiſts wiſe reaſon then a Proteſtants folly. Beſides, the terme of Popiſh, indeed doth rather give force to their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then weaken them, when a Papiſt ſpeakes againſt Popiſh Intereſt. And ſo doth this and other <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Authors, who ſpeake herein againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and Popiſh intereſt in <hi>England,</hi> (under Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth)</hi> and in <hi>Holland;</hi> So he uſeth the word Popiſh to his owne diſadvantage. And now having added two Queſtions, he leaves the Matter in Queſtion, under Queſtions. To <hi>Paraeus</hi> who ſaith, Vſurping <hi>Nimrods</hi> power was of God, and muſt be obeyed; He anſwers, <hi>He beleeves</hi> Nimrods <hi>Vſurpation was over a people not engaged by Oathes and Covenants.</hi> So here hath hee given up the maine Queſtion it ſelfe, That uſurped po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer may be obeyed, if there be no Oathes and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants. Thus there remaines now no doubt of the maine poſition; But all the doubt is come to Oathes and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, ſo that we have nothing now to doe, but to cleare Oathes and Covenants. As for <hi>Bucers</hi> Teſtimony, he feſſeth his blindneſſe, <hi>that he ſees not how it can be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> Neither doe I thinke he will ever ſee as long as the webb of prejudice and partiality covers his eyes. Yet in this blindneſſe, he kicks and throwes at <hi>Bucer,</hi> becauſe he hardly toucheth his Gall; and yet out of partiall love to <hi>Paraeus,</hi> he grants him the very ſame for <hi>Nimrod,</hi> which here he denies to <hi>Bucer.</hi> As for his <hi>obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cting Iack <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de againſt</hi> Bucer, why doth he not object alſo the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165237:7"/> uſurpations of <hi>William Rufus, Henry</hi> the fourth, or <hi>Hen.</hi> the ſeventh, who not having right Titles to the Crown, might be encouraged, as well as <hi>Jack Cade?</hi> But the name of <hi>Iack Cade</hi> he thinks may ſerve for a ſtumbling block to a blind Reader, whereas he that ſeeth, will ſtep over both that and the reſt. This man no queſtion hath heard, that God is the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and diſpoſeth all things as he pleaſeth; And if he pleaſe to give a people into the hands and power of ſuch a one, (as he hath often done) will or can this man reſiſt and overcome the higheſt? or will he reſolve not to obey them whom God is reſolved to ſet over him? If ever he <note place="margin">Dan. 8. 18. 25. 35.</note> be reſtored to his right reaſon with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> he will confeſſe, <hi>That the moſt High doth rule in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will, and ſets up over it the baſeſt of men.</hi> Let him pitty, and not damne, the once famous, and now diſtreſſed, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Churches in Greece, who lye under the weight of ſuch baſe and heavy Vſurpations, and yet yeild obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Vſurpers. Beſides, the ground of obedience being in regard of an authority, gotten by a prevaling <note place="margin">Page 5.</note> power; Is it to be thought, that any who have an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to uſurpe authority, and have power to get it, will if there were no ſuch Doctrine, forbeare uſurpation, or leave it when they have gotten it, and can keepe it by power? Againe doth not this objection lye againſt the Demurrers yeilding his purſe to ſave his life? for doth not he here encourage a theefe to goe on in his thefts? But if he pleaſe, he may find an anſwer to both, that theſe conſequences ratioanally come not from the ones gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his purſe for his perſonall ſafety, nor from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers giving obedience for publique peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165237:8"/> As <hi>for his preferring of Sathan to Magiſtracy,</hi> When <hi>Paraus</hi> ſpeakes ſo much of an Authority given from God to Sathan, in regard of power, as he did to <hi>Nimrod;</hi> I will not ſay this Demurrer [p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rhaps] will believe the one, and obey the other; But certainly he doth now in his falſe accuſation (without any <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus)</hi> obey him that is the Accuſer of the brethren.</p>
            <p>Page 6. <hi>He findes himſelfe in a ſtraight when either he muſt obey, or elſe bring confuſion to a Common Wealth.</hi> But not to obey he is reſolved, and therefore by beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the queſtion, or rather granting it to himſelfe, he breakes through. He ſaith, It is a ſinne to obey; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this very argument of confuſion is brought to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew, that it is not ſinne but a duty; <hi>And in</hi> Nimrods <hi>caſe, and elſe where (with a perhaps)</hi> he grants it lawfull. And <hi>for his conſequences of not recovering from Bondage,</hi> let him give me the ſame leave he takes to ſay, <hi>He muſt not do evill that good may come thereof;</hi> He muſt not diſobey to avoid theſe conſequences: But the grand Caſe (though the little Caſe will not) very fairely acknowledgeth; <hi>That where lawfull and unlawfull are in queſtion, conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and inconvenience muſt keepe ſilence.</hi> Neither are theſe conſequences ſo neare, and certaine, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion by diſobeying. Beſides, there have beene often remedies for ſuch conſequences; for often, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations having been upon this very Crowne, they have often been removed. And <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> leaving his people (upon the very ground, and poſition of the Author oppoſed by the Demurrer) to obey the <hi>French,</hi> who had the preſent power over them, yet the <hi>French</hi> afterward were expulſed. That of the Maſters mate he can neither anſwer, nor ſuffer. He ſaith, <hi>His</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:165237:8"/> 
               <hi>Right muſt not be acknowledged;</hi> whereas there is no ſuch thing in the queſtion, but whether his commands ſhould be obeyed for the ſafety of the Ship. And then according to his uſe, he helps his lame anſwer over the ſtile, with Oathes and Covenants; with are another buſineſſe. Yet neither is here a withdrawing from a bleſſed union, but a preſervation of the Common-Wealth from deſtruction, which by being deſtroyed can hardly preſerve the bleſſed union; yet here ſomewhat bountifully, <hi>He juſtifies (with his uſuall perhaps) thoſe that are forced to proſecute ſutes under the preſent C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urts.</hi> Yea, <hi>He conſents to the power that there manageth the lawes with a diſtinction:</hi> But doe not all his objections of breaking Oathes, allowing uſurped power, and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie poſt factum,</hi> come in now againſt himſelfe? For if the Judges have no Authority as well as power, doth not this ſubmiſſion incourage, approve and abet an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped Authority? And what ſatisfaction can this give to any man, with a quiet conſcience to enjoy that which they decree to him? No more then if a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour meeting two that have a ſuite in law, ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the law to be for one, and againſt the other; ſhould that one ſatisfie his conſcience in taking the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſtate into his poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion? Therefore if he will uſe the word juſtifie with ſence and reaſon, he muſt allow an Authroity, which in a caſe of uſurpation is grounded on a tacite and interpretative conſent; <hi>He would have all joyne together in diſobeying, and that indeed is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne:</hi> But firſt, that is unprofitable; yea, in being over power'd, it is impoſſible to any good effect, becauſe thus joyning, it will bring indeed a diſjoyning, taking away all juſtice, and order, give up all to power, and ſo bring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165237:9"/> confuſion to the whole. And could not the Papiſts whom he accuſeth of nicetie, have found out this groſſe anſwer, in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> yet they never urged it, and therefore were more reformed in the Doctrine of obedience, then this Demurrer.</p>
            <p>And having walked through his diſcourſe, with Oathes continually in his mouth, now he is come to the right place of uſing them; for all this while his uſe of them hath beene but generally a granting of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for upon the matter it ſpeakes this, that if it were not for Oathes, obedience were due. But to ſay that the Kings perſon cannot dye, is a matter of Mirth, or if you will of Non-ſenſe; eſpecially to be put into this Oath; for it amounts to this, that I ſweare to preſerve the Kings perſon, which needes no preſervation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot dye; As for the clauſe <hi>of preſerving the Priviledges of Parliament, and Liberties of the Subjects;</hi> which is the maine force, and little elſe ſaid by him; I firſt deſire an anſwer of this queſtion: Did this objector urge this Oath out of any Pulpit or Preſſe, with this Vehemencie and Iteration againſt the breach of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges by the Prentiſes? or was it ſo preſt againſt thoſe that ſate ſome dayes, and for ought apeares, would have ſate till this day, if they had power, while many of the Members were driven away? And here, upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion let the Demurrer know, that though the combin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation which managed that breach, were ſaid to have many ſcore thouſands in that engagement to abet it, and were confident of prevailing, or elſe would never have undertaken it; yet the Author (though hearing this) did not for any place of profit apply himſelfe to that party, but (as by many witneſſes can be proved)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165237:9"/> reſolved to leave both his place, and any place in the Kingdome, and began a journey to goe out of both; But that God wrought a change. And indeed I cannot blame him, if it were abominable to him to live under ſuch a Government, it being one of the higheſt Curſes; <hi>The rule of Children, and one of the baſeſt Vaſſalages to be ruled</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>by them:</hi> And yet upon their Rule and Law-making did this engagement, Act and proceed; Yea, the Houſe it ſelf; yet Oathes then not preached as now. So by a ſecond experiment it apperes, he could part from a place of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, if he ſaw reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>But if we looke to the Oath it ſelfe, doth the Oath <note place="margin">The words of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venat are theſe, wee ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reality and conſtancy in our ſeve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor with our eſtates and lives mutually to preſerve the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp;c.</note> bind us actually to preſerve the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or onely to endeavour to preſerve them? For actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to preſerve them, may be, and is often out of our power, and then we ſhould ſweare to doe that which is impoſſible for us to performe. If this Demurrer had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſumme of money, and had ſworne that he would indeavor to preſerve it ſafe for the owner; but a Robber takes this ſumme by force from him, or will kill him, if he doe not deliver it; is this man guilty of Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if having ſincerely intended, and endeavoured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, yet in theſe caſes he part from the money?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, is the giving of all to confuſion by diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the way to keepe priviledges of Parliament, and liberties of the people; or rather the way to looſe both Parliament and Liberties, and to give up all to a popular confuſion, or to a Military power to be ruled by force, and not by lawes? Breifely, if obedience be a duty in regard of Common good, (which is the generall Tenet held forth by Divines, and Caſuiſts) how doth an Oath binde to the breach of a duty, or to the deſtruction of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165237:10"/> the Common-Wealth, which indeed was made for the preſervation of it? And let the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer ſay ingenuouſly whether he thinkes that ſuch a deſtructive ſenſe was the meaning of the Oath, and ſo Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily underſtood by the Givers or Takers.</p>
            <p>And now Page 8. He goes about to prove that the Heire is already a Succeſſor, and yet complaines that ſome keepe the Heire from being a Succeſſor; and after (not by a Popiſh nicety, but a Popiſh abſurdity) he maintaines the inceſtuous Title of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and calls her Hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the Crowne. And herewith another [perhaps] He ſpeakes that which is uncharitable with it, and untrue without it; and nothing but want of charity would have ſpoken an untruth in a ſcandalous manner, though with a [perhaps.] For the Gent. hath beene excuſed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Age in point of attendance, and ſo the Demurrer having taken back to himſelfe his owne uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and untruth, (for perhaps cannot make that to have bin true, which whatſoever happen was not true) he hath nothing left to helpe him, but confeſſion and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment.</p>
            <p>But to draw to an end, I wiſh that this Demurrer would ſo farre know himſelfe, that he is moſt unfit for dealing in controverſies; being moſt irreſolute in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and therefore unfit to reſolve others: He hath at his back both a wall, and a back-doore, when he is bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine queſtion, then he runs to the wall, but ill daw bed of Oathes and Covenants; and when he is preſt not onely by Arguments, but his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to confeſſe the Truth, he leaves open a back doore call'd [perhaps] to ſhift himſelfe out: But let him know that at this doore the poſition which he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165237:10"/> may get out alſo. For example; among many [perhaps] he ſaith thus: A people may [perhaps] law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <note place="margin">Page 2.</note> obey a Government, when there is no proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of recovering their loſt Government. Here if it be inferred, that there is no probability of recovering, He hath left a [perhaps] to get out of the concluſion. But his oppoſer will tell him that with the ſame [perhaps] his poſition may be true and eſcape alſo. So Page 3. When an unlawfull power commands lawfull things, a man [perhaps] may obey: If ſo, Then [perhaps] the Author affirming the ſame thing, may have ſaid true: And if ſo, why is this party ſo angry and uncharitable, without a [perhaps] for that with [perhaps] may be true? But thus it falls out, when men are reſolved to fight with a truth that ſtares in their faces; the truth breakes out of the mouth of their conſcience, and then they put a Muzell called [perhaps] upon it, that it may not ſpeake plaine. What is this, but to impriſon the truth in unrighteouſneſſe, to leave people in doubt, whom they undertake to reſolve, by blind gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the blind, to leave them in the Darke, that they may not know where nor whether to goe, and at laſt fall into the Ditch? Let him ſee the truth himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he undertake to teach others. Let him receive the Truth fully, and that ſhall make him fully free. Free from error, free from uncharitableneſſe, and ſlanders, the fruits of it. Let him not out of prejudice againſt the Truth, and the Author that maintaines it, make Warre againſt <hi>Calvin, Bucer, Paraeus, Gualter, Peter Martyr;</hi> and if he have Charity to forgive them, let him enlarge it a little to forgive the Author alſo, that ſayes after, and with them. But indeed there is little
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165237:11"/> cauſe for him to give, but much to receive forgiveneſſe. For in his Title, having called himſelfe a lover of Truth and Peace, even in the very face of that Title, and in the ſame Page; he is not aſhamed to utter ſuch untrue ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, that he confutes his owne Name, by groſſe eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhewing that he loves neither truth nor peace. And whereas ſundry other perſons that have written on this Subject, have dealt like men of Religion and Reaſon, anſwering Matter with Matter, Reaſon with Reaſon; This Demurrers tongue being ſet on fire of Hell, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers Matter and Reaſon with Scandalous untruthes. And this I charge upon his Conſcience, wiſhing that the worme of guilt may never leave biting, untill by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe it worke Repentance, and by Repentaece For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
